Guide to the Everett Cherrington Hughes Papers 1922-1982
University of Chicago Library
Hughes, Everett Cherrington. Papers
1922-1982
73.5 linear feet (147 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The papers of Everett Cherrington Hughes comprise 73.5 linear feet of professional material. The papers document his career as a sociologist and educator, as well as his research in occupations, race relations, and education. The collection consists of a large body of correspondence; course materials from McGill University, the University of Chicago, Brandeis University and Boston College, and lectures, articles, book reviews, and translations. The collection also includes research material, travel diaries, and memoranda by Hughes; studies on occupations done for Canada's Royal Commission on Bilingualism and Biculturalism, and his studies on undergraduate and medical education carried out at the University of Kansas. Some material by Helen MacGill Hughes on the American Sociological Association's Ad-Hoc Committee on the Status of Women in the Profession can also be found in this collection.
Information on Use
Access
The Everett Cherrington Hughes Papers are unrestricted and open to use by researchers with the exception of three portions of the collection:
1) Carnegie Corporation Project, interview by Isabel S. Grossner, Oral History Research Office, Columbia University, transcript, with annotations by Hughes (located in Series I Box 1, Folder 10). Researchers may consult the oral history interview, but must secure permission to cite or quote its contents from Columbia University, Oral History Research Office, New York, NY 10027.
2) Series VIII, Audio-Visual Materials, is currently restricted due to its fragile condition or need for special equipment.
3) Series IX, Letters of Reference, Grant Evaluations, and Referee Reports, is restricted and will not be open to researchers until the year 2030.
Biographical Note
Everett Cherrington Hughes was born on November 30, 1897. He was the son of a Methodist Episcopal minister who believed firmly in the equality of Black and white people, advocated for education, and disapproved of drinking, card playing and dancing. Many members of the Hughes family had attended college at Ohio Wesleyan, and Everett did as well beginning at the age of 16. Hughes received his B.A. from Ohio Wesleyan in 1918.
After graduation Hughes taught English to the workers of the Wisconsin Steel Works at Chicago. It was here as Hughes worked with immigrant factory workers that he was made aware of the importance of ethnic identity. From there he worked for Upper Peninsula Industrial Relations Association in Escanaba, Michigan from 1920-1922. Hughes then was awarded a Centenary Fund grant from the Methodist Church with which he studied the community of Pullman, Illinois, under the guidance of Garrett Theological Seminary.
In the fall of 1923 Everett Hughes enrolled at the University of Chicago as a graduate student in sociology and anthropology. Hughes studied under Robert E. Park, Ernest W. Burgess, Ellsworth Faris, Robert Redfield, Ruth Shonle Cavan, Nels Anderson, and other noted scholars. He maintained his residence in Pullman and found a job as the director of Mark White Square Park for the South Park Commission. This job provided Hughes with a rich location to do sociological research. He took students there to do field work and produced a study on the police for Ernest W. Burgess.
In 1925 he met Helen Gregory MacGill and they were married in August of 1927. Helen became an active partner in many of Hughes's projects.
Just before completing his dissertation in 1927 Hughes was offered a position at McGill University in Montreal with Carl A. Dawson, another University of Chicago graduate. At this time McGill University was the only university in Canada to offer a program in sociology, and Dawson and Hughes became the first two members of that department. Hughes received his Ph.D. degree in 1928. His dissertation, The Growth of an Institution: The Chicago Real Estate Board was first published in 1931 by the Society of Social Research of the University of Chicago.
Hughes established his research interests in the fields of race and ethnic relations, industrialization, and occupations. In 1931-1932 Hughes was the recipient of a Social Science Research Council Fellowship to Germany to study the Catholic labor movement in the Rhineland. He planned his research in Germany to complement his work on French Canada. In the late 1930s he and Helen did a study of the change in a French Canadian town as it industrialized under English Canadian management. Just as the research on this project was completed, Everett Hughes was offered an assistant professorship at the University of Chicago in 1938. Hughes accepted the job and French Canada in Transition was eventually published in 1943.
Hughes remained at the University of Chicago until 1961. He was promoted to associate professor in 1943, and professor in 1949. He served as chairman of the Department of Sociology between1952 and 1956. During World War II he became a member of the Committee on Human Relations in Industry along with George Brown, Allison Davis, Burleigh B. Gardner, Frederick Harbison, Robert J. Havighurst, Neil Jacoby, W. Lloyd Warner, and William Foote Whyte. The Committee was a business and academic partnership to study industrial society. A few corporations supported the Committee to achieve its research. Industry and Society was published in 1946 and Hughes's contribution was chapter 6, "Race Relations in Industry." Hughes published other books and articles in the 1940s and 1950s reflecting his continuing work in the areas of race relations, professions, and occupations. Some of these publications includes: Where Peoples Meet: Racial and Ethnic Frontiers, (1952) by Everett C. Hughes and Helen M. Hughes; Men and Their Work, (1958); and Twenty Thousand Nurses Tell Their Story: A Report on Studies of Nursing Functions Sponsored by the American Nurses' Association by Everett C. Hughes, Helen M. Hughes, and Irwin Deutscher, (1958).
During his tenure at the University of Chicago Hughes's activities show evidence of his commitment to Robert Park as a mentor and his training at the University of Chicago as a sociologist. He revived Robert Parks's course on race relations and transformed it into a course on the African novel that he began to teach at Brandeis University in 1961. Hughes was also a member of the Committee on Education, Training, and Research in Race Relations with Louis Wirth, Robert Redfield, Fred Eggan, Sol Tax, Allison Davis, Ralph W. Tyler, and Frederick Harbison. He participated in the efforts to aid German universities after the war through the University of Chicago's Committee for Aid to German and Austrian Scholars. He held visiting professorships at Frankfurt University through the exchange program in the years 1948, 1953, and 1958. His article "Good People and Dirty Work" came from his first tour there in 1948. Hughes also continued to develop courses in field training for sociologists.
In the 1950s Hughes became a member of the Committee on Human Development and began to take a more active interest in the sociology of education. Through this committee he established ties to Kansas City, where the committee had been doing research. Hughes began working with professors at the University of Kansas Medical School in 1952. The study of the Medical School developed into a study of the undergraduate college with the encouragement of Dean George R. Waggoner. The two monographs that resulted from these studies were Boys in White by Howard S. Becker, Blanche Geer, Everett Hughes, and Anselm Strauss, (1961), and Making the Grade by Howard S, Becker, Blanche Geer, and Everett Hughes, (1968). Hughes carried on his involvement with medical education when he joined the American Medical Association's Citizens Commission on Graduate Medical Education from 1963 to 1967.
As the studies at the University of Kansas were underway, Hughes moved to Boston and began teaching at Brandeis University in 1961. During this same academic year he served as president of the American Sociological Association.
Still in contact with many colleagues in Canada, Hughes received an invitation to propose a study to the Canadian Royal Commission on Bilingualism and Biculturalism in 1963. This commission was appointed by the Canadian Government to study ways in which to cauterize the crises between French and English Canadians. By this time his book French Canada in Transition had long been a classic text in Canadian sociology. In 1965 he took leave from Brandeis University for a year and accepted a joint visiting professorship at McGill University and the Université de Montréal. During this year he taught and pursued a project approved by the Royal Commission using students from both universities to assist in the fieldwork. His final report "Career Patterns of Young Montrealers in Certain White Collar Occupations," was completed but never published.
In 1968, Hughes moved his activities to Boston College after becoming an emeritus at Brandeis. He taught at Boston College until he gained emeritus status there in 1976. During the 1970s Hughes enjoyed advising students from both Brandeis University and Boston College. He also participated in another study funded by the Carnegie Commission on Higher Education, Education for the Professions of Medicine, Law, Theology, and Social Welfare, by Everett C. Hughes, Barrie Thorne, and Agostino M. De Baggis, (1973).
Everett Cherrington Hughes died in Boston on January 4, 1983, at the age of 86.
Scope Note
The Everett Cherrington Hughes Papers have been divided into nine series: (1) Personal, (2) Professional Correspondence, (3) Course Work, (4) Writings and Research Material, (5) French Canada Studies, (6) University of Kansas Studies on Medical and General Education, (7) Helen MacGill Hughes, (8) Audio-Visual Materials, and (9) Letters of Reference, Grant Evaluations, and Referee Reports.
The concentration of material covers the period of the 1960s and 1970s. Two heavily documented projects from the late 50s and 60s are projects done at the University of Kansas on general undergraduate and medical education (1952-1964) located in Series VI, and the study for Canada's Royal Commission on Bilingualism and Biculturalism (1963-1965) located in Series V.
The collection includes Hughes's diaries that included field notes, memoranda, and diary entries along with personal and professional observations. Hughes dictated the memos with an audiograph, and a secretary transcribed them in duplicate or triplicate. The transcriptions and tapes are located in Series VIII. The memoranda are found in a concentrated group now found in Series IV. We have maintained Hughes's filing system. The travel diaries have been grouped together in Series IV.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Hughes, Everett Cherrington, 1897-; Hughes, Helen McGill, 1903-; Anderson, Nels, 1889-; Becker, Howard Saul, 1928-; Geer, Blanche; Lamontagne, Jacques; Park, Robert Ezra, 1864-1944; Riesman, David, 1909; Westley, Margaret; American Medical Association -- Citizens Commission on Medical Education; Social Science Research Council (U.S.) -- Committee on Sociolinguistics; Canada -- Royal Commission on Bilingualism and Biculturalism; University of Chicago -- Dept. of Sociology; University of Chicago -- Committee on Human Relations in Industry; McGill University -- Dept. of Sociology; Brandeis University -- Dept. of Sociology; Boston College -- Dept. of Sociology; American Sociological Association -- Ad Hoc Committee on the Status of Women in the Profession; American Sociological Association; Community Studies–Kansas City, Mo.; University of Kansas; Biculturalism -- Canada; Bilingualism -- Canada; Chicago school of sociology; Sociology -- United States; Sociology -- Canada; French-Canadians; Occupations -- Sociological aspects; Professions -- Sociological aspects; United States -- Race Relations; Sound recordings
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal
  Series I, Personal, consists of curriculum vitae, bibliographies, awards received, interviews, and biographical and autobiographical essays. In particular, there is an annotated bibliography of works by Hughes that was probably compiled by Helen Hughes around 1967. The series includes essays by other authors on the Chicago school of sociology. Also included are Hughesís reminiscences of student days in Chicago, written in memoranda form in the late 1970s. The memos recall course work, attitudes, and interests of both graduate students and professors, as well as stories of Robert Park, Nels Anderson, Robert Redfield, Helen MacGill, and Ruth Shonle Cavan.
  - Vitae, resume of services at Brandeis University, 1965-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annotated bibliography, ca. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Address books, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Teaching offers, correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Itineraries, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Everett C. Hughes, "My Personal Experience of Race," paper for discussion at Session 72, American Sociological Association meeting, August 31, 1967 (Accession 97-57) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hughes family history, memoranda, notes, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "In honor of Ralph C. Hughes, February 29, 1968 being his Seventeenth Birthday, His coming and some of his goings as recorded by his father, Charles Anderson Hughes, His mother, Jessamine Blanche Roberts Hughes, is in the record too," typed transcript of diary entries compiled by Everett Hughes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Corporation Project, interview by Isabel S. Grossner, Oral History Research Office, Columbia University, transcript, with annotations by Hughes, 1967 [permission to cite or quote must be obtained from Columbia University, Oral History Research Office, New York, NY 10027] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Autobiographical essay in letter to Robert J. Havighurst attached to: "Life After Sixty," survey, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Autobiographical memoranda, University of Chicago student days, notes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Autobiographical memoranda, University of Chicago student days, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interview with Bob Weiss, transcript, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - University of Chicago, student notes, class handouts, final examinations, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - University of Chicago, Robert Park, Newspaper course, "The Press Agent by Margaret Bonar, Everett Hughes, A. P. Butler, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - University of Chicago, Robert Park, Social Survey course, handouts, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - University of Chicago, Robert Park, Human Ecology and Human Migration course, notes by Hughes and Helen MacGill, 1920s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, Ellsworth Farris, Social Attitudes course, notes, final exam, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, outlines of sociology courses prepared for Sigma Theta, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago, "Realtors as a Professional Group," typescript, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, Ph.D. qualifying exams, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, papers on the Chicago School of Sociology: (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Seventieth birthday, correspondence, clippings, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Boston College, honorary LL.D. degree, commencement program, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Institutions and the Person: Essays Presented to Everett C. Hughes, correspondence, reviews, manuscripts, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Synopsis of the Round Table in Honor of Everett C. Hughes," Seventh World Congress of Sociology, Varna, Bulgaria, September 14-19, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ostow, Robin, "The Institutionalization of Sociology in English and French Canada: The Career of Everett Cherrington Hughes," manuscript, annotated by Hughes, mid-1970s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Boston College, "A Series of Four Public Lectures to Honor the Scholarly Contribution of Its Distinguished Visiting Professor, Everett C. Hughes," announcement, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Sociological Association, Community Section Awards "Statement in Honor of Everett Cherrington Hughes," by David Popenoe, Toronto, manuscript, correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series II: Correspondence
  Series II, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by name. The concentration of material dates from the 1960s and 1970s but includes letters as early as 1926 and as late as 1982. The correspondence is professional and includes other types of materials such as manuscripts, conference papers, and meeting minutes. There is an extensive exchange with David Riesman, Nels Anderson, Allison Davis, Meyer Fortes, Clifford Geertz, Erving Goffman, Andrew M. Greeley, Robert Havinghurst, Morris Janowitz, Margaret Mead, W. Lloyd Warner, and Leslie A. White. Hughesís work with the Social Science Research Council's Committee on Socio-linguistics and American Medical Association committee work are represented in this series.
  - A, general, 1960-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Abramson, Harold J., 1963, 1971, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Adams, Samuel C., 1950-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Adler, H. G., 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Adler, Judith, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Aldine Press, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Aldine Press, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Aldine Press, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Aldine Press, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Aldine Press, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Aldine Press, 1972-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Alfred A. Knopf Incorporated, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, prize committee, 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Conference on Ethnic Problems in the Contemporary World, October 26-28, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Conference on Ethnic Problems in the Contemporary World, papers, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - American Anthropological Association, 1962-1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - American Assembly, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American Journal of Sociology, 1961-1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Journal of Sociology, 75th anniversary issue, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - American Journal Sociology, policy, University of Chicago, Department of Sociology, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - American Medical Association, Council on Medical Education and Hospitals, Selected Papers from the Annual Congress on Medical Education and Licensure, 1958, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - American Medical Association, Council on Medical Education and Hospitals, Selected Papers from the Annual Congress on Medical Education and Licensure, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - American Medical Association, Citizens Commission on Graduate Medical Education, minutes, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - American Medical Association, Citizens Commission on Graduate Medical Education, minutes, papers, reprints, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - American Medical Association, Citizens Commission on Graduate Medical Education, precis of meetings, papers, reprints, notes, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - American Medical Association, Citizens Commission on Graduate Medical Education, precis of meetings, papers, reprints, notes, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 4-8)
  - American Medical Association, Conference on Regional Medical Programs, press copies of papers presented, Washington Hilton Hotel, Washington, D.C., January 15-17, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - American Medical Association, National Conference on Medical Ethics, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - American Sociological Association, 1963-1980 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - American Sociological Association, 1963-1980 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - American Sociological Association, ad hoc committee of sociologists for peace in Indo-China, 1967-1970 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - American Sociological Association, ad hoc committee on the status of women in the profession, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - American Sociological Association, American Sociological Review, 1963-1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - American Sociological Association, procedures and nominations, 1963-1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - American Sociological Association, San Francisco meeting, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - American Sociological Association, San Francisco meeting, "Personal Experiences and Race Relations," 1967 (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - American Sociological Association, San Francisco meeting, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - American Sociological Association, Denver, Colorado meeting, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - American Sociological Association, sociolinguistics, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - American Sociologist, 1968-1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Aminoff, Tonia, 1967-1976 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Anderson, Nels, 1965-1980 (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
  - Anderson, R. Bruce W., 1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Arensberg, Conrad M., 1941-1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Association for the Study of Grants Economy, Aaron, Henry, "Implicity Transfers to Homeowners in the Federal Budget," 1969 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - B, general, 1953-1981 (Box 8, Folder 9-13)
  - B, general, 1953-1981 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Bain, Robert, 1953-1959 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Baldwin, Burt R., 1969-1972 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Banton, Michael, 1961-1979 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Barnes and Noble, Incorporated, 1961-1974 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Barnes, John A., 1959-1976 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Barrett, Russell, 1963-1975 (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Basic Books, 1963-1971 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Becker, Howard S., 1955-1978 (Box 9, Folder 11-13)
  - Becker, Howard S., 1955-1978 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Bedminster Press, Incorporated, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Behavioral Science Book Service, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Benney, Mark, 1968-1974 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Bernard, Jessie, 1961-1976 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Bierstedt, Robert, 1966-1975 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Binstock, Jeanne S., 1964-1974 (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
  - Blau, Peter, 1959-1969 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Blumer, Herbert, 1966-1976 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Blumer, Herbert, "The Blumer-Hughes Talk," 1969 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Bodemann, Y. Michal, 1967-1980 (Box 10, Folder 14-15)
  - Bodemann, Y. Michal, 1967-1980 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Bolton, Charles D., 1959-1969 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Borinski, Ernst, 1963-1980 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Boston College, general, 1963-1980 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, Ritchie P. Lowry, chairman, 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, Lynda L. Holmstrom, assistant chairperson, 1970-1974 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, Lynda L. Holmstrom, chairperson, 1974-1979 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, graduate program, 1966-1969 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, graduate program, 1966-1969 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, course lists, 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, course lists, 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, course lists, 1973-1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, course lists, 1974-1975 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, course lists, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, course lists, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Boston College, Department of Sociology, 1970-1978 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Boston College, expenses, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 9)